O.W. Riegel Papers WLU.Coll.0387
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
- Southern Interscholastic Press Association (SIPA), 1937-1991; 2.5 Linear Feet (Box 1-6, Folder 1-117)
  Items in this series are relevant to the Southern Interscholastic Press Association. Within this series are correspondence between speakers for the conventions and O.W. Riegel, photographs of the annual convention, SIPA programs, Quill and Scroll Banquet artifacts, and speech excerpts from the various speakers. Some items and subjects of note include correspondence regarding the permission of black delegates during the process of desegregation, a scrapbook of events during the 1959 SIPA convention, a scroll from the 1954 Quill and Scroll Banquet, and a penant commemorating the SIPA conference. Major correspondents and speakers include: Cartoonists Ken Bald and John Mendelsohn, Congressman John Moss, James P. Warburg, Ferdinand Kuhn, and Abe Jones.
  Riegel, O. W. (Oscar Wetherhold); Moss, John E. (John Emerson), 1913 - 1997
  - Awards, 1937-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    this subseries focuses on the winners of various awards over the years of the SIPA conference at Washington and Lee University. Most items consist of list of winners and press releases.
    - Awards, 1937-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Items in the folder consist of lists of award winners in the various SIPA competitions including best Newspaper, Yearbook, Magazine, and Radio broadcast.
    - Awards, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Awards Luncheon, 1957-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Items in the folder consist of lists of seating charts for the front table at the SIPA Awards Luncheons
    - Complimentary Lists, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Items in the folder consist of annual lists of attendies who were to receive complementary accomodations to certain SIPA events.
  - Correspondence A-J, Kenneth Bald; Cole, Fred Carrington; Gaines, Francis Pendleton (Box 2, Folder 5-40)
    This box of correspondence contains the only topical correspondence folder in the series, highlighting letters written that centered around the issues of desegregation and the contested permission of black delegates to SIPA. Afterwards, correspondence is alphabetical. Several renowned figures collaborated with O.W. Riegel by hosting their own sessions at the SIPA conference. Some of these figures include cartoonists Kenneth Bald and Douglas Borgstedt. Washington and Lee presidents Fred Cole and Francis Gaines are also included in this part of the collection.
    Kenneth Bald; Cole, Fred Carrington; Gaines, Francis Pendleton
    - Desegregation, 1954-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Agr-Arm, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Ken Bald, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Bar-Bec, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Beeler-Beh, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Col. J.W. Benjamin, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Benz-Bon, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Borgstedt, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Bort-Bro, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Buch-Bur, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - William Burton, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Cam-Car, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Cat-Chil, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - C. Clark Chism, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Cli-Coc, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Dr. Cole, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Coo-Cun, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Dav-Dic, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Dickler-Dur, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - E, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Fis, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Fle-Fri, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Dr. Gaines, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Gar-Gram, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Grav-Gre, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Paul Green, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Gri-Gut, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Haf-Ham, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Han-Hill, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Hob-Hopk, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Kathrine E. Hopper, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Hot-Hur, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Jac-Jen, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Jes-Joh, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Abe D. Jones, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - A.H.W. Jones- Jud, 1930-1970 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence K-Z (Box 3, Folder 41-78)
    Riegel corresponded with approximately 200 individuals reagarding events and issues with SIPA. This subseries contains correspondence with all individuals with last names beginning with K or later.
    - Kan-Kee, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Bradley Kelly 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - bradley Kelly 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Bradley Kelly 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Koo-Kuh, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Lea-Ley, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - ernest K. Lindley, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Lyl-Lyo, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Marya Mannes 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Marya Mannes 1963 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - McD-Meg, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Men-Mey, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Mic-Mil, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Mof-Mos, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Mot-Muri, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Murp-Mus, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - N-O, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Pace, W-Packett, H., 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Packett, J-Park, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Parsons, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Pax-Pre, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Rea-Res, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Rho-Rus, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Sag-San, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Sav-Ser, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Sea-She, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Howard K. Smith, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Smith, S-Sou, 1930-1990 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Spi-Swe, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Tan-Tow, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Tra-Two, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - V, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Wal-War, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Wat-Whi, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Wid-Will, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Wils-Wri, 1930-1970 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Unk./Mult. People 1952-1961 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Unk./Mult. People 1962-1968 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - News and Photos, 1931-1989 (Box 4, Folder 79-100)
    The contents in this box consist of photographs of SIPA events, news publications about SIPA, a few high school newspapers submitted to the SIPA competition, financial documents, executive committee notes, the SIPA constitution and bylaws, and samples from SIPA's annual current events quiz. Some items of note include a 1937 satirical edition of Thomas Jefferson High School's student newspaper, The Jeffster, and photographs of the SIPA Awards banquet from 1953 and 1955.
    - Current Events Quiz, 1938-1968 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Finances, 1947-1968 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Leadership, 1952-1974 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Newsletters 1973-1981 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Newsletters 1985-1989 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Newspapers 1935-1951 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Newspapers 1956-1986 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Photos 1931-1939 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Photos 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Photos 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Photos 1941-1947 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Photos 1947-1953 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Photos 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Photos 1954 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Photos 1954-1959 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Photos 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Photos 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Photos 1962-1967 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Photos Misc. and Negatives, 1938-1968 (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Presidential Campaigns, 1938-1968 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Publications 1931-1978 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Publications 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Programs and Speeches, 1930-1991 (Box 5, Folder 101-103, Box 1-2)
    Items in this sub-series consist of speeches and speech excerpts by various SIPA conference speakers, and programs for the SIPA conference from 1930-1968, along with a few programs from the 1980's and 1991. Some of the speeches are stored in smaller boxes because they are printed on index cards. Additionally, there is a scroll from the 1954 Quill and Scroll banquet, housed in this sub-series in order to save space.
    - Programs, 1930-1991 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Speeches, 1956-1963 (Box 5, Box 1)
    - Speeches, 1964-1968 (Box 5, Box 2)
    - Speeches, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Speeches Misc., 1930-1991 (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Scroll, 1954 (Box 5)
  - Instructions, Speaker Materials, and Misc., Kenneth Bald (Box 6, Folder 104-117)
    The contents in this sub-series consist of artifacts from the Quill and Scroll Banquets, SIPA delegate registration instructions, the lodging needs of SIPA speakers, materials given to Riegel by speakers, additional instructions to staff, and miscellaneous items in the SIPA series. Some objects of note include a SIPA penant with Washington and Lee enscribed on it, A scrapbook of the events from SIPA in 1959, and Admission tickets to the 1954 SIPA events.
    Kenneth Bald
    - Quill and Scroll Banquet, 1937-1959 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Registration, 1958-1968 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - Room Needs and Reservations, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Schedules, 1950-1957 (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Speaker Materials Bald-Foster, 1930-1968 (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - Speaker Materials Harrington-Lasswell, 1930-1968 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - Speaker Materials Mannes, 1930-1968 (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - Speaker Materials Mandelsohn-Moss, 1930-1968 (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - Speaker Materials Rau-Wylie, 1930-1968 (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - Staff Instructions, 1958-1967 (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - Miscellaneous, 1942-1952 (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Miscellaneous, 1954-1968 (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - Scrapbook, 1959 (Box 6)
  - Unprocessed Materials, 1935-1970 (Box 6a)
- Virginia Politics, 1974-1982; Riegel, O. W. (Oscar Wetherhold); McGovern, George; 1.1 Linear Feet (Box 1, Folder 1-26)
  Items in this series relate to Virginia Democratic Politics from the early 1970s to the early 1980s. Riegel was a member of the Rockbridge County Democratic Committee and attended the Virginia State Democratic Convention. His records include political correspondence between congressman Olin, delegate Davis, other local candidates, and party members.
  Riegel, O. W. (Oscar Wetherhold); McGovern, George
  - Alice Rabe, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    Alice Rabe was a candidate for the Virginia House of Delegates seat representing Rockbridge County, Lexington, Buena Vista, Bedford County and the city of Bedford. Riegel gave advice and support for Alice in her campaign. Items in this subseries consist of correspondence between Riegel and Rabe, campaign materials, such as planned ads, and clippings relevant to the campaign.
    - Campaign Materials, 1974-1977 (Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1977 (Folder 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1974-1977 (Folder 3)
  - Cadwell Butler, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
    Congressman Butler represented Virginia's 6th Congressional District. Within this subseries is a series of correspondence mostly from Riegel on various political topics. Most of Butler's correspondence consists of his periodic newsletters to his constituents.
    - Cadwell Butler, 1977-1978 (Folder 4)
    - Cadwell Butler, 1979 (Folder 5)
    - Cadwell Butler, 1980-1983 (Folder 6)
  - Campaign Items, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Campaign Reports, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9-14)
    Riegel's political correspondence within Virginia consists of over 20 correspondents, primarily on the topic of campaigns and elections. Some correspondents include former House of Delegates member Jim Davis, Delegate candidate Sprong, and democratic party officials.
    - Advertisement Campaign, 1974-1982 (Folder 9)
    - And-Fitz, 1974-1982 (Folder 10)
    - Godwin-McL, 1974-1982 (Folder 11)
    - Pag-Spo, 1974-1982 (Folder 12)
    - Wei, 1974-1982 (Folder 13)
    - Misc., 1974-1982 (Folder 14)
  - Henry Howell, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Jim Davis, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Jim Olin, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17-21)
    Jim Olin was the congressional representative of Virginia's 6th district after Cadwell Butler. This subseries consists of correspondence between Riegel and the Congressman. The main topics discussed are funding for the "MX Missle" and issues over Olin's congressional fundraising operation in the mid to late 1980s.
    - Jim Olin, 1982-1983 (Folder 17)
    - Jim Olin, 1983-1984 (Folder 18)
    - Jim Olin, 1984 (Folder 19)
    - Jim Olin, 1985 (Folder 20)
    - Jim Olin, 1985-1986 (Folder 21)
  - National and State Democratic Committees, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rockbridge County Democratic Committee, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
    This subseries consists of correspondence by county democratic officials to local democratic party members concerning campaign actions and fundraising. Riegel was a member of the Rockbridge County Democratic Committee.
    - Committee Rules, Members, and Statements, 1974-1982 (Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1982 (Folder 25)
    - Notes & Misc., 1974-1982 (Folder 26)
  - Unprocessed Materials, 1974-1982 (Box 1a)
- Hungary (Not Yet Processed), 1945-1947; Riegel, O. W. (Oscar Wetherhold); 2.2 Linear Feet
  After World War II, Riegel worked as a U.S. diplomat in Hungary. This subseries consists of items related to his time there. Items of note include his diplomatic ID, hungarian currency, hungarian newspapers and magazines, Monthly reports on his work in Hungary, and detailed notes on events he experienced while there.
- Film (Not Yet Processed), 1950-1980; 6.5 Linear Feet
  Riegel was an avid collector of film related material, particularly from European sources. During his travels in Europe, Riegel attended numerous film festivals and kept materials from a variety of films. Additionally, he taught a course on motion picture and there are numerous items related to that course. Items of note include publications from an international film festival in Czechoslovakia, Film Festival attendance buttons, samples of film with descriptions of how film is used in the motion picture, and student work from Riegel's motion picture course he taught at Washington and Lee University.
- Unprocessed Materials, 1902-1993; Riegel, O. W. (Oscar Wetherhold); 23.25 Linear Feet
  The rest of the collection is still being processed. We anticipate additional series' to be added to the collection upon their completion. Some anticipated series include: Film, Riegel's early life, Pre-War Travel, Early Academic Work (undergrad and grad school, Mobilizing for Chaos and Crown of Glory, Communications Institutions (such as the International Association of Mass Communication Research), The Science Service, and Riegel's East-Germany Survey.